Guide to the Bureau of Applied Social Research records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Bureau of Applied Social Research Records,
1944-1976
Columbia University. Bureau of Applied Social Research.
103 boxes
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
5012632
History
The Bureau of Applied Social Research, headed by sociologist Paul Lazarsfeld, was established in 1944 and helped make Columbia a pioneering institution in the social sciences. Through empirical research, ideas regarding the functioning of individuals and groups were developed and tested. Many ground-breaking studies were conducted by Lazarsfeld and his colleagues, among the most important of which was the impact of radio and television on the American public. Through such work, the Bureau become the "birthplace" of mass communication research. Many survey techniques were developed at the Bureau, such as the focused interview and panel interviewing methods. The Bureau was eventually succeeded by the Center for the Social Sciences in 1976.
Scope and Content
Project materials, including reports, monographs, books, articles, Masters essays, Doctoral dissertations, foreign publications, and audio-visual materials.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 11 series:
Series I: Project Index
Series II: Project Proposals
Series III: Reports
Series IV: Masters Essays
Series V: Doctoral Dissertations
Series VI: Articles
Series VII: Personnel Published and Unpublished Materials
Series VIII: Additional Project Files and Miscellaneous Materials
Series IX: BASR Library Materials and Publications
Series X: Center for the Social Sciences
Series XI: Card Catalog of BASR Library
Subjects
Bureau of Applied Social Research.; Lazarsfeld, Paul Felix.; Berelson, Bernard, 1912-1979.; Glock, Charles Y.; Merton, Robert King, 1910-2003.; Social sciences--Research.
Access Restrictions
This collection is shelved off-site and requires advance notice of intent to use.
This collection has no restrictions.
- Series I: Project Index
  Boxes 1-103.& This Index is intended to show the entire output of each Bureau project. The projects were assigned numbers that were generally chronological, beginning with the year the project began, but became chronologically disordered from B-1000 to B-1038 due to a transition in the numbering system introduced in 1964. For these projects, the year of initiation is given after the project title.
  Within projects, publications are listed by type: Reports, Monographs, Books, Articles, Masters Essays, Doctoral Dissertations, Foreign Publications and, in a few cases, Audio-Visual Materials. Within each category, publications are ordered by year and then alphabetically by author. If an author produced more than one publication of a given type in a particular year, a number in parentheses indicates its order in that author's publications for that year.
  Projects that were funded through the Bureau and approved by its Board as "Bureau Projects" have numbers preceded by "B." Faculty projects, for which the Bureau provided space or services but that it did not initiate as an organization, are indicated by an "F." Similar student projects are indicated by "S" or "D." The names of the original project directors are given in parentheses after the project title.
  - Project Files Index Introduction (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld and Edward A. Suchman Initial Report on an Exploratory Study of Coverage by Radio Stations., 1941, (6 pp. plus charts Questionnaire, notes on staffing coverage.) (Box 1, Folder B-0061-1)
    [Examples of data available about kind of audiences government agencies may reach by sponsoring radio programs, such as availability of people, general listening habits, station and program preference.]
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld, M. Bayne and Edward A. Suchman Station Coverage Report. 1941, ( 60pp. Report) (Box 1, Folder B-0061-2)
    [Discusses availability of people as listeners, information on station coverage and program structure. Questionnaire to stations included: What America Listened to on Wednesday, Dec. 4.]
  - Ernest Dichter Study of Psychological Programs., 1939., ( 41 pp. Study Notes) (Box 1, Folder B-0065)
    [From interviews, which are given verbatim, two major themes were found in the various self-improvement programs. They offered explanations of psychological facts and they appealed to the listener to overcome difficulties or to accept unchangeable situations. The resultant good or bad effects upon the listener are discussed.]
  - Julia Hoffard Musical Listening, 1939 (Box 1, Folder B-0071)
    [file on musical listening]
  - Jack N. Peterman, Trienah Meyers Lucky Strike Hit Parade, 1940, (B-0075-1: 20 pp., B-0075-2: 23pp. 3 folders containing lecture by Adorno, Audience measurement booklet- Zeisel & Polygraph, Study & notes on music and radio, Notes on Lucky Strike report) (Box 1, Folder B-0075-1)
    [Reports- B-0075-1: Discussion and report on how to better the Hit Parade rating system which measures relative popularity of songs. B-0075-2: A comparison of Hit Parade ratings, using different methods. Description of moves of five places or more in one week by Hit Parade songs. How eight songs moved. Hit Parade weaknesses.]
  - Typed report on Princeton project and Columbia report on BASR from 1968-69; 1 separate pamphlet, 1940, ( 5 folders containing ) (Box 1, Folder B-0076)
  - Lazarsfeld, Berelson, & Gaudet Voting Study: How the Voter Makes Up His Mind in a Presidential Campaign, 1940, (35 folders containing ) (Box 2, Folder B-0080)
    [Folder 1 empty, Folder 34 missing, two folder 35's, Code for Erie, Peoples Choice- Sandusky
    (The People's Choice: Erie County Study: Sandusky Study) (note, there was no report submitted). Book: Lazarsfeld, Berelson, & Gaudet 1944]
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld and Marjorie Fleiss Attitude Toward Spending, 1940, (4 folders containing notes, questionnaire, cards & tests, questionnaire and typescript) (Box 2, Folder B-0092)
    [B-0092-1: 40 pp., B-0092-2: 13 pp.
    A scale was set up based on questions which reflected people's spending habits. B-0092-2 consists of interviewers'comments on the spending test survey. Reports: B-0092-1, B-0092-2]
  - Marjorie Fleiss, and Paul F. Lazarsfeld Bloomingdates Restaurant Study, 1940, (3 folders containing Reports, Bloomingdale Restaurant study, card coder) (Box 2, Folder B-0093)
    [Would customers feel Bloomingdale's service to them was curtailed, would prestige of store be lowered, do financial returns of restaurant justify its upkeep? Stratified by income of 421 respondents. Report: B-0093-1]
  - Lazarsfeld & Gaudet Shortwave Radio Listening in Erie County, 1940, (4 folders containing Memos, Repsondent lists, questionnaire, draft reports) (Box 2, Folder B-0105)
    [Report: not available]
  - T.W. Adorno Analytical Study of the NBC Music Appreciation Hour, 1940, (1 folder containing study, draft report) (Box 2, Folder B-0107)
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld American Station Sampler and How to Use It., 1940, (6 pp.: 1 folder containing Codebooks) (Box 2, Folder B-0110)
    [A chart listing 11 separate sets of radio stations-all stations in U.S. and territories included. Discussion of station sampling procedure. One empty folder with contents in Vienna.]
  - R. Arnheim and E. Suchman Small Stations Foreign Language Broadcasts, 1941, (B-0121-1 40 pp., B-0121-2 80pp.:3 folders containing Study report, Instructions to field supervisors, Codebooks) (Box 2, Folder B-0121)
    [B-0121-1 Preliminary analysis: number of hours and what language, types of programs, news items-domestic or foreign, drama-local or foreign, types of national appeals, etc. B-0121-2: This paper presents available evidence on the problems of such broadcasting. A questionnaire was filled out by 66 specially appointed listeners covering 800 hours of foreign language broadcasts across the country. They also could present summaries of their observations. Published. See pp. 3-64 in Radio Research 1941. Reports: B-0121-1, B-0121-2 1940 Article: Arnheim & Bayne 1941. One empty folder with copy of contents in Vienna. ]
  - Suchman & Friedrich Italian Language Program Audiences, 1941, (4 folders: 1 is missing, 2&3 are empty with copies of contents in Vienna, 4 contains Codebook and Questionnaire instructions ) (Box 2, Folder B-0122)
    [Report: B-0122-1; B-0122-2 Monograph: Suchman 1941]
  - Herta Herzog Minority Groups and the 1941 Mayoralty Election, 1941, (25 pp.: 1 empty folder with copy of contents in Vienna) (Box 2, Folder B-0125)
    [A discussion of how the decision for whom to vote in the 1941 mayoralty election will be determined by racial and national fears and prejudices. Based on 57 detailed interviews among Jewish, Italian, Irish and German people. Report: B-0125]
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld, Arnheim, Herzog, Knupfer The Daytime Serial (Soap Opera Study), 1942, (51 pp.: 11 folders containing Questionnaires, Questions & memos, draft reports, (folders 5-7 are empty with a copy of the contents of #5's contents in Vienna), Analysis, Content Analysis, Analysis- Soap Opera in Italian ) (Box 2, Folder B-0130)
    [This sets forth the social and commercial problems created by daytime radio serials, reviews what is known, and suggests areas which need further exploration. The research methods which might be used are also discussed.]
  - Herta Herzog Daytime Serials: Their Audience and Their Effect on Buying, 1942, (Pages:100 pp.: 4 folders containing Questionnaires) (Box 2, Folder B-0131-1)
    [Based on survey of 5000 women, this gives a broad general picture of women's daytime listening habits and the effect of listening upon actual use of product advertised.]
  - Herta Herzog News and Views on John B. Hughes, 1942, (4 folders containing codebooks) (Box 2, Folder B-0131-2)
    [Hughes was a commentator who took over Raymond Graham Swing's time spot on the radio. This is a discussion of his selection and treatment of topics, comprehensibility, voice, opinion shaping, and comparison with other commentators. How to sell the product advertised on his program is also discussed.]
  - Herta Herzog Study on Stomach Distress, 1942, (4 folders containing Codebook and studies) (Box 2, Folder B-0131-3)
    [310 interviewed, questionnaire included. Attitudes toward stomach troubles, remedies.]
  - Herta Herzog Preliminary Test of Six Kolynos Commercials, 1942, (66 pp. Studies) (Box 3, Folder B-0131-4)
    [75 respondents were asked to compare commercials and were then interviews about them and about their own dentifrice use. Scripts and questionnaire included.]
  - Herta Herzog Test of Kolynos Tooth Powder Commercials, 1942, (35 pp. ) (Box 3, Folder B-0131-5)
    [Desc:100 women heard four sets of Kolynos Tooth Powder commercials and were then interviewed about them and about their own dentifrice use. Scripts and questionnaire included. (missing file)]
  - Herta Herzog Test on Bisodol Commercials, 1942, (50 pp. ) (Box 3, Folder B-0131-6)
    [76 people interviewed, questionnaire included. Problems posed were straight talk versus dramatized technique, personal versus straight descriptive approach commercial, as well as what properties of Bisodol should be stressed, sketchy versus detailed. (missing file)]
  - Genevieve Knupfer The Buying of Vitamin Preparations, 1942, (35 pp. ) (Box 3:, Folder B-0131-7)
    [Topics covered are who buys vitamins, how much do they spend, brands bought. Questionnaires included. Problems with the data supplied by Industrial Surveys Co. are discussed. (missing file)]
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld Daytime Music Programs, 1942, (1 folder containing report) (Box 3, Folder B-0135)
    [Assembles available information on whether and what kind of daytime musical program would reach middle-aged, middle-class women. Main source of data: survey of 5000 women in 1941 by Office of Radio Research. Report: B-0135]
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld Saturday Evening Post Study, 1941, (1 folder containing Research suggestions) (Box 3, Folder B-0136)
    [This contains several reports dealing with the characteristics of Saturday Evening Post readers
    Report: B-0136. One empty folder with copy of contents inVienna.]
  - Manuel Manfield and Jeannette Green Greeting Card Study, 1941, (52 pp. 1 empty folder with copy of contents supposedly in Vienna ) (Box 3, Folder B-0140)
    [193 persons interviewed by questionnaire and conversational interviews. Report discusses type of people interviewed, what greeting cards mean to people, resistance to them, cards as merchandise, the dealer. Questionnaires included. Report: B-0140]
  - M. Bayne Refrigerator Buying, 1941, (30 pp.: 1 empty folder with copy of contents in Vienna. 1 folder containing Questions) (Box 3, Folder B-0141)
    [Based on 60 detailed interviews, a tentative analysis tries to answer such questions as: Do people have more subtle desires to which we could link the use of a refrigerator? Could we mobilize psychological forces which usually are not thought of in refrigerator ads? Report: B-0141]
  - Durant & Lazarsfeld Morale Survey, 1941, (2 folders containing Questionnaires) (Box 3, Folder B-0142)
    [Report: not available Article: Lazarsfeld & Durant 1942 Masters Essay: Durant 1943]
  - Magazines vs. Radio Serials, 1941 (Box 3, Folder B-0143)
  - Leo Lowenthal Biographies in Popular Magazines. Published. See pp. 507-548 in Radio Research 1942-1943., 1942-1943, (14 folders containing Data, Notes & tables) (Box 3, Folder *B-0145)
    [Article: Lowenthal 1944]
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld Joint Ownership of Radio of Radio Stations and Newspapers, 1941, (Pages:B-0150-1 35 pp., B-0150-2 34 pp., B-0150-3 55pp., B-0150-4 35pp.: 21 folders and 2 loose leaf code binders Folders 1-3 are empty with copies of their contents inVienna (statistical jargon covers by radio affiliation), other folders contain Report Analysis, Misc., Tabulations & tables, Tables & codebooks, Questionnaires, Reports, Misc. codes, and Codebook binders) (Box 3 & 4, Folder B-0150)
    [B-0150-1 A statistical picture of distribution of newspapers and radio stations, and some of their main characteristics in the whole country. B-0150-2 An analysis of 93 1-1 communities for which newspaper ownership of more than 50% is claimed. (1-1 community: radio stations and newspaper associated.) Power, frequency, population, newspaper circulation, network affiliation are variables taken into account. B-0150-3 Discusses in what communities newspapers disappear and the role in this disappearance played by radio and newspaper-radio affiliations. B-0150-4 50 radio stations were selected which were associated with a newspaper. 50 stations and 50 newspapers were selected which were not associated or owned one by the other. Then the 50 associated and non-associated stations were compared. Same was done for the 2 groups of newspapers. Reports: B-0150-1 through B-0150-4 1941 Articles: Lazarsfeld 1942 (1,2)]
  - Jeannette Green Drugstore Survey, 1943, (66 pp.: 3 folders containing Questionnaire, Tables, and one Empty file with a copy of the contents in Vienna) (Box 4, Folder B-0151)
    [Report based on 264 interviews in 13 cities, concerns attitude toward drugstores and pharmacists. Report: B-0151-1; B-0151-2]
  - L. Kay H. Herzog Attitude Towards Life Magazine, 1943, (B-0152-1: 16 pp., B-0152-2: 60 pp., B-0152-3: 14pp.: 19 folders and 2 loose leaf binders 2 Empty folders with copies of contents in Vienna on the observations on the readings, others containing Analysis, Progress reports, Questionnaires, Tables, Correspondence & memos, Questionnaires & codes, Analysis & reports, Binders- interview data) (Box 4, Folder B-0152)
    [B-0152-1 intensive interviews were conducted toward a better understanding of the function of Life magazine as a medium of communication and as a social and political magazine. B-0152-2 Perceptions of Life's editorial policy, Life compared with other magazines, why some don't read it, how thoroughly it is read as a news magazine, as a non-news magazine, as a picture magazine. Based on 200 interviews. Questionnaire included. B-0152-3 General reading habits of Life, Saturday Evening Post, Collier's and Liberty readers; relation of multiplicity of magazine reading to intensity of reading. Reports: B-0152-1 through B-0152-3]
  - Lazarsfeld, Kaufman, Herzog Iowa Survey of Radio Listening. Published. (See pp., 130-151 in Communications Research, 1948-1949.), 1948-1049, (4 folders containing Questionnaires, Codebooks, Memos) (Box 5, Folder *B-0153)
    [Articles: Herzog 1944, Kaufman 1944, Kass 1949 Masters Essay: Kass 1945]
  - Gerhart Wiebe Refuting Wartime Rumors, 1942, (35 pp.: 1 empty folder with copy of contents supposedly in Vienna) (Box 5, Folder B-0156)
    [Excerpts from three broadcasts were studied to find their relative merit in terms of audience appeal and their effectiveness in "scotching" rumors. Program Analyzer and supplementary questionnaire were used. Questionnaire included. Report: B-0156]
  - Ernest Dichter Health Program Study., 1942, (43 pp.: 1 empty folder with copy of contents in Vienna) (Box 5, Folder B-0158)
    [To establish the appeal of radio health programs, 14 people were interviewed and these interviews are given verbatim. A combination of factors was found to explain their continued interest. Report: B-0158]
  - Goodwin Watson Wine Study, 1944, (48 pp.: 9 folders containing 1-4 folders are empty with copies of Wine study contents in Vienna, other folders contain Questionnaires, and Code Books) (Box 5, Folder B-0160)
    [Previous discussions of customs and wine drinking, social factors involved, special characteristics of wine drinkers, types of drinkers and the marketing of wine are summarized. Topics for further study are suggested. Original discussions are contained in interim reports under B-0160. Report: B-0160-1 through B-0160-4]
  - Kaufman "Why We Fight" Analysis, 1942, (Memos and Tests Report) (Box 5, Folder B-0162)
  - Maurice L. Farber Program Analyzer Test of "Ask Eleanor Nash.", 1942, (6 pp. Empty File, copyof contents in Vienna ) (Box 5, Folder B-0163)
    [This report discusses the test group, their "like" and "dislike" reactions, reactions to Eleanor's voice and to the program as a whole. 18 women were in the sample. Report: B-0163]
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld Magazine Reading Before and After Pearl Harbor, 1942, (22 pp.: 3 folders containing Memorandums, Study Codes) (Box 5, Folder B-0165)
    [Based on data obtained from Life, Inc., and Hearst Publications, Inc., this report investigates the changes in people's reading habits as a result of Pearl Harbor, especially with regard to the reading of nonfiction articles concerned with the war. Report: B-0165]
  - Ruth A. Durant The Structure and Stability of Public Opinion; Some Aspects of National Morale, Masters' Essay, 1942 (Box 5, Folder B-0166)
    [Masters Thesis Corresponds to S-0166. Report not available]
  - Ruth A. Durant The Structure and Stability of Public Opinion; Some Aspects of National Morale [Master's essay}, August, 1942, (121 pages plus appendices ) (Box 5, Folder S-0166)
  - Shortwave Broadcasts to Germany and Italy, 1942, (56 pp. ) (Box 5, Folder B-0167)
    [Discussion of unfavorable aspects of the programs and of technical problems. Report: B-0167. 1 Empty folder with copy of its contents in Vienna.]
  - Lowenthal and Lazarsfeld Philadelphia News and News Commentators Study, 1942, (11 folders containing Tables, Codes,Notes, Commentaries, Analysis, Analysis of NY paper editorials, Memoranda, Monitors, Procedures) (Box 5, Folder B-0168)
  - Peatman & Marcson "This is War" Program Tests, 1942, (3 folders containing Memos, and Codebooks, 1 is empty with a copy of its contents-the report in Vienna.) (Box 5, Folder B-0169)
    [Report: B-0169-1; B-0169-2]
  - Herta Herzog Pretesting a Short Story, 1942, (15 pp.: 4 folders containing 1 Empty Folder with copy of Report in Vienna), others contain Story, Misc. memo, Pretesting- 8 questionnaires (confidential)) (Box 5, Folder B-0170)
    [Summary of findings of a reader test of 15 people to determine reactions to characters, plot, etc., of readers of a preliminary version of a novelette. Interviews and questionnaire included. Report: B-0170]
  - Jeannette Green Golden Wedding Whiskey Study, 1943, (18 pp.: 2 folders containing 1 empty folder with contents in Vienna), other contains Questionnaire) (Box 5, Folder B-0181)
    [163 interviews were conducted with Protestant, Catholic and Jewish men and women to find out if the wedding ring on the Golden Wedding (whiskey) trademark was offensive to their religious and social feelings. Questionnaire included. Report: B-0181]
  - Genevieve Knupfer Poughkeepsie Social Stratification Study, 1943, (6 folders containing Study, Correllations, Misc., Questionnaire, Codebook) (Box 5, Folder B-0182)
    [(Also filed as S-0285) Report: not available Article: Knupfer 1947 Dissertation: Knupfer 1946]
  - Kay Birthday Cards Study, 1943, (3 folders containing Questionnaire, Memo, Draft report) (Box 5, Folder B-0183)
    [Report: Not available]
  - Marjorie Fiske Promoting Radio to Retailers, 1943, (57 pp. Report) (Box 5, Folder B-0185)
    [The successful commercial use of radio rests upon an understanding of the interrelationship of the commercial and the informing and entertaining aspects of radio. This memorandum then, deals with "general psychology of radio, its power as a selling force, and some particular aspects of retailers' use of radio." Report: B-0185 Article: Fiske 1944]
  - Robert K. Merton Patterns of Influence (Time Readership in Dover, N.J.), 1943, (102 pp. Report) (Box 5, Folder B-0187)
    [This report explores the meaning of influence in a community and its relation to the reading of Time magazine. In two field trips 86 interviews were secured from three groups of people: 1) influential people, 2) Time subscribers, 3) random people. Suggestions for further research are made and interview schedules are included. Report: B-0187 Article: Merton 1949]
  - Jeannette Green "American Magazine" Study, 1943, (34 pp.: 21 folders 1 Empty folder with contents of the study in Vienna, others contain Questionnaires- 8 interviews, Codes- & codesheets, Interview instruction, Questionnaire, Tables, Misc., Procedures, Study comparisons, Criticisms, Preference trends, Commercial breakdowns, Gratifications, Psych. applied to publishing, Pages from magazines, Final study) (Box 5, Folder B-0190)
    [315 people were interviewed, showing American Magazine steering a middle course between Cosmopolitan and Saturday Evening Post. Among people who read American Magazine, four main gratifications came to light. Report: B-0190]
  - Herta Herzog "The Negro and the War"-Test of an OWI Pamphlet, 1943, (22 pp.: 18 Folders Folders Contain Questionnaires, Misc., Memos, Overall summary, Survey tables, Worksheets, Interview notes-instructions and correspondence, Scripts and script substitution, Commercials,, Question analysis, Stations responding, Statistical data, Comment analysis and one empty folder whose contents are supposed to have a copy in Vienna.) (Box 6, Folder B-0192)
    [Outlines responses of 70 Blacks interviewed to pamphlet itself and to idea conveyed by it that they should strongly support the war effort. Report: B-0192]
  - Marjorie Fiske Retailers' Use of Radio, 1943, (19 pp.: 13 folders containing Questionnaires, Questions & codes, Codes, Interview instructions, Iowa study, Bibliography of department store study, Memos, Script materials, Study quotes, Analysis-tables) (Box 6, Folder B-0195)
    [200 housewives were interviewed as to how local stores' advertising could be made most helpful with emphasis on use of radio. Questionnaire included. Report: B-0195-2]